Guest: Can you hear me?
Justin: Yeah, I can hear you.
Guest: Okay, so when I prove you wrong, I want you to say to your life, I'm sorry.
I won't.
All right?
You won't.
Perfect, all right.
I know.
Justin: Every Christian I talk to is the only Christian doing it right, and I'm sure you're about
to crash out in like five seconds.
So are you at least 18?
Guest: Yes.
Justin: Fantastic.
And do you know that the Bible condones slavery?
Guest: No it doesn't.
So let's go back to Genesis chapter 15 verses 13 to 16.
Justin: This is going to be painful, so I'll just read it for you since you haven't read it.
It's okay.
I got it right here.
I read it.
I'm sure you have.
Fantastic.
As for your male and female slaves you may have, it is from the nations around you that
you may acquire male and female slaves.
You may also acquire them from among the aliens residing with you, and from their families
who are with you who have been born in your land.
They may be your property.
You may keep them as a possession for your children after you, for them to inherit to
as property.
Now, what do you call it when you own another human being as property?
Slavery.
Oh, slavery.
The Bible condones slavery.
So now I want you to issue an apology.
Guest: No, let me finish speaking though.
Justin: Oh, let me, we'll try this again.
And does owning another human being make them a slave?
Yes.
Okay, did God just say, these are the slaves you may own?
Guest: Okay, can I finish speaking?
Justin: Did God just say, these are the slaves?
Did God say, did God say, did God say you can own these slaves?
Guest: He said it for a reason.
Justin: Did he say, did he say you can do it?
Guest: Yes, for a reason.
Justin: Okay, so then God condones slavery.
That's literally what I said.
the Christian God condones.
For a reason.
Thank you.
Okay, so now I want you to issue an apology before we move on to your next talking point.
Guest: Can we, okay, I'll say sorry for that, yes, God does condone for a reason.
Justin: Fantastic.
So now we got to talking point number two, God allows slavery and you think you've got
a good reason for it.
Guest: For a reason, for a reason.
Yes, for a reason.
By the way, can we agree that he's speaking to the Israelites in that verse, yes or no?
Justin: Yeah, God is speaking to Moses in order to speak to the Israelites.
Guest: To the Israelites, perfect, all right.
Justin: Go to Genesis 15.
Genesis 15 is going to cook you, you're not going to like this at all.
Guest: 13 to 16.
13 to 16.
You're going to hate this.
All right, perfect, all right.
Justin: This is not going to go the way you think it is.
As the sun was going down and a deep sleep fell upon Abram and a deep and terrifying
darkness descended upon him, then the Lord said to Abram, know this for certain that
your offspring shall be aliens in a land that is not theirs and they shall be slaves there.
They shall be oppressed for 400 years, although it's technically 430 years.
Guest: Yep, 435 if you want to be exact, but he's talking about the Israelites, they're going
Justin: to be.
Actually, I think it's 430.
I mean, I'm pretty sure it is.
Guest: But he's speaking to the, he's saying that the Israelites are going to be enslaved, correct
or yes?
He's speaking about the Israelites, correct or not?
Justin: He's talking about the Israelites serving in Egypt.
Guest: Perfect, okay, then when we go back to the same verse you were talking about previous,
he's allowing the Israelites to have slaves up to six years.
Justin: Yeah, it says the time that the Israelites lived in Egypt was 430 years.
Alright, apology, apology number two, let's have it.
Guest: Okay, I'm sorry for that, yeah, 430, I'm sorry, wow.
Justin: Fantastic, okay, alright, now back to your bad talking point.
So what about Exodus?
Guest: So back to your verse, correct?
Justin: Which one?
Guest: It's the previous one he gave me, correct?
Justin: Leviticus 25.
Guest: Yes.
Alright, what about it?
He's telling the Israelites that they have the right to own a slave up to six years and
free them the seventh year, yes or no?
Justin: Citation needed, you're lying.
Guest: Go back to the verse then, go back to the verse.
Justin: I got it right here, you're not going to like it.
I love how confident these people come in having not read the book.
Alright, so show me in Leviticus 25 where it says anything about going free in the seventh
year.
Guest: Here.
Justin: You're confusing Exodus 21 with Leviticus 25 by the way, just be clear.
Guest: Give me one sec, I was eating.
Justin: It's wild how often Christians get spanked on this topic considering they've got the
power of the Holy Spirit.
Why is the Holy Spirit so weak?
Guest: Go to Exodus 21.
Justin: I told you, you're confusing Exodus 21 and Leviticus 25, I already got it, fantastic.
This is going to cook you.
Guest: No it isn't.
Justin: Yeah, you're not going to like this at all.
It says, when you buy a male Hebrew slave, he shall go out, I'm sorry, he shall serve
you six years but in the seventh year he shall go out a free person without debt.
Now, what if you're a woman though?
Uh-huh.
Have you read verse 7?
When a man sells his daughter as a slave, yeah, she doesn't get to go out.
And what happens if somebody is given a wife while they're in their six years of service?
If a master gives them a wife and she bears some sons or daughters, the wife and her
children shall be her masters and he shall go out alone because they are permanent slaves.
Guest: Okay, now go to verse 10, read verse 10.
Justin: If he takes another wife to himself, so now we've got polygamy, if he takes another wife
to himself, he shall not diminish the food, clothing, or marital rights of the first wife.
Yeah, if he takes a wife, because you're allowed to take multiple wives.
Guest: So if you, if, I'm going to repeat that again, it says if he takes another wife, so if he
takes another wife, he shall not diminish food, clothing, and uh, right, yeah, right?
Of who?
Which is implying of the woman that was sold.
No.
Justin: Which means the woman.
Wrong.
Yes, that's what it says.
Guest: How's it wrong?
Justin: That, you're not to diminish the woman's sustenance while she is a concubine.
Just like everything else, you haven't actually read the text, we'll read it for you.
When a man sells his daughter as a slave, she shall not go out as the male slaves do.
If she does not please her master, who has designated her for himself, then he shall
let her be redeemed.
Why does it say that he has designated her for himself?
Why does it say that he doesn't answer my question?
Why does it say that he designated this woman?
What's it mean when it says that she's been designated?
Guest: If you go back to the old Hebrew text, it says serve.
Justin: What's it mean, Deuteronomy is not the old Hebrew text, Exodus is older.
Guest: I'm talking about Exodus, I'm talking about the verse we're talking about.
Justin: I know, we're in Exodus, I'm asking you a question about the passage in Exodus that
we literally just read.
It says that if he designates her for himself or for the son, what does it mean to designate?
Guest: In the old Hebrew text of that verse, it says serve.
Justin: Stop saying Hebrew, you don't know Hebrew.
Guest: Well, if you go to blueletterbible.org, it translates it for you.
Justin: I actually know Hebrew, we're going to get into this.
Okay, so Solo says, oh jeez, if I worship this god, if I worshiped a god this bad, I'd
stop voting.
Big W Solo, I appreciate that, and I agree, I hope this guy doesn't vote.
All right, so the problem here is that you're interpreting the word evid or ama to mean
what?
Guest: Excuse me, sir, you got a…
Justin: Which word?
Evid or ama?
Guest: Search it up in the blue letter at Bible.org, it tells you itself.
Justin: I'm literally telling you what the words are.
A male Hebrew slave is an evid.
So what's your complaint with the Hebrew?
Guest: The lettering was changed.
What lettering?
To serve.
Justin: No, incorrect.
Guest: Search it up, you can pull it up on your screen right now.
Justin: And this guy is just a glutton for punishment.
All right, we're going to do Exodus 21, and we'll do, which verse do you want to read?
Guest: You go to 1 Timothy 1.10.
Justin: That's in Greek, it's not even the same book.
We're talking about what's happening in Exodus 21.
Guest: So you just want to talk about Old Testament, not New Testament?
Justin: So you're just dodging the passage.
You're right, if I was in this conversation and I was in your position, I would buy a
ticket to get the fuck out of here real fast, because you're getting absolutely roasted
right now.
This is embarrassing.
So we're talking about what Exodus 21 says, and you're trying to run away from it now.
So I want to know what in Exodus 21 gets is getting translated incorrectly.
Guest: Well, you're misreading it, so.
Justin: What am I misreading?
Guest: Do you keep interrupting me?
Can I go?
Justin: I asked you, you said I'm misreading.
I want to give me the actual text that I'm misreading.
Guest: Okay, I'm giving you verses and you keep saying I'm jumping around.
These verses answer themselves.
Justin: They don't.
Guest: They do.
Well, back then in the Bible, it states if you were in debt and you didn't have the money
to pay for it, you became a servant, which was called a slave in those days, and you
worked for free.
Justin: I'll help you out.
Do you see this?
Yes or no?
You're wrong.
I'm fixing it for you.
Do you see this word right here?
Right.
That's a radicalized consonant at the end.
This means, sorry, hold on, there we go.
That's actually not the right one.
Sorry.
We want this word.
There we go.
Evin.
This means a slave or a servant, right?
We also have the word ama in here somewhere in verse seven.
If we go to verse seven, we'll find a different word for a female slave.
Guest: But it says a servant right there.
Justin: I know.
I'm about to help you out.
Just hold on tight.
Okay, so we have another word that we find here.
This is an ish for a male and a daughter, which is a bat, or if it's plural, it's going
to be different.
There we go.
And this is ama.
So this root here means a female slave.
This is a preposition.
That's not part of the word.
Okay, so these are the words that we have.
And both of these words can mean a servant or a slave.
Do you know what the difference between a servant and a slave is?
Guest: Well, a slave doesn't get paid.
And what else?
Well, they get treated poorly.
Justin: No, one goes free and one doesn't go free.
Guest: Well, yes.
What I'm trying to say-
Justin: Fantastic.
In verse seven, do the female slaves get to go free?
Guest: If you go back to what it says-
Justin: In verse seven, do they get to go free?
It's a yes or no question.
Guest: It doesn't say if they get to go free.
Justin: It says the opposite.
It says they don't get to go free.
If you go to verse four about the woman who is given as a wife to the temporary servant,
do they get to go free?
Guest: Well, yeah.
Justin: No.
It says if a master gives him a wife and she bears some sons or daughters, the wife and
her children shall be her masters and he shall go out alone.
So they don't get to go free.
That's called slavery.
Imagine to have this much confidence to get up here and alive thinking you're going to
educate somebody and floundering in literally just three inches of water.
You're literally drowning in a bathtub that just got turned on.
We're not even deep yet.
Guest: It says right here, but if the servant declares, I love my master and my wife and my children
and do not want to go free, then his master must take him before the judges.
Justin: Yeah.
And pierce his ear.
I know.
And why would he do that?
Why would he make that decision?
Guest: Well, that's if he wants to keep them.
Justin: Yes, because he doesn't want to get his family split up.
Yes, because these people are permanent slaves.
They are permanent slaves owned by the Hebrews.
And if somebody gives you a slave and they bear children to you, your only option, your
only option is to become a slave yourself.
You don't get to keep them.
Guest: You're misreading that again.
Israelites were enslaved for 400 years.
Justin: No, this is after.
This is after.
Guest: Yeah, this is exactly.
So God's telling them, you guys are, yeah, I give you my right to own slaves for six
years and then you can free them the seventh year.
Justin: Except for the women, it says, if his master gives him a wife and she she bears him sons
or daughters, the wife and her children shall be her masters and he will go out alone.
The man is leaving alone.
The man's wife and the children remain property of the master.
Guest: Yes.
I just said that God gave them the right to own slaves.
I know.
After they were enslaved.
Justin: I know.
Fantastic.
We finally got it.
Yes.
God said you could own slaves.
That's what background says.
The Christian God condones slavery.
I'm glad we can finally come to an agreement on that.
Guest: You're misreading it again.
Justin: OK.
What did I misread?
Guest: You're putting it.
Well, you're putting it into text like he he thought it was OK for to own slaves out
of the random.
He said you can do it.
He.
After they were enslaved for four hundred and thirty years, he said, you can do it.
Justin: You can own slaves.
He just doesn't want them to be enslaved by another nation.
Guest: Well, they were enslaved for four hundred and thirty years.
Correct or not?
Justin: Yes.
And then God say and then God saved those people.
Did he free all the slaves on the planet?
Guest: Oh, no, obviously not.
Justin: Oh, OK.
Who did he free?
Guest: The Israelites.
Justin: Did he free the slaves owned by the Israelites?
Guest: Well, the men, yes, but the woman.
Justin: Wrong.
No, no.
When they left, when they left Egypt, they already did.
You know that when they left Egypt, they they're some of them own slaves.
Guest: Well, yes.
Justin: OK.
Did God tell them to free the slaves?
Guest: It doesn't say the quote.
Justin: OK, so God says you can own slaves.
He tells you who you can own as slaves.
He says you can beat your slave.
Never once did he say that you can't own slaves.
Guest: OK, and then go to Deuteronomy 11 to 14.
Justin: I love Deuteronomy 11.
I love Deuteronomy 11.
It's one of my favorite chapters.
Guest: 15 to chapter 15 verses 11 to 14.
Justin: Oh, you're not going to like this at all.
I love how they get up here thinking I haven't read it.
All right.
Deuteronomy chapter 15 11.
Since there will never cease to be some in need on the earth, I therefore command you
open your hand to the poor and needy neighbor in your land.
Say slave.
Guest: Now, read verse three.
Justin: Of a foreigner you may exact it, but you must remit your claim on whatever any member of
your community owes you.
This is talking about lending an interest in collecting debts.
So in the book of Deuteronomy and in the book of Exodus, we have laws about what kind of
debt and what kind of interest you can charge.
And as it turns out, you can lend money at an interest to foreigners, but you couldn't
do it to your own fellow Hebrew Israelites because God has separate laws for what you
can do to your brothers and separate laws to what you can do to the foreigners.
You can charge interest to the foreigners.
You can go to war and kidnap the foreigners.
You can enslave the foreigners.
You just can't do it to your own fellow Hebrews unless they're women, because women are just
as bad as foreigners.
Guest: It's telling you to cancel the debt.
Justin: It doesn't say that.
That's if they're your own fellow Hebrew and it's in the year of Jubilee.
Have you never read the book?
What garbage website are you pulling these talking points from?
Because they're all garbage talking points.
Guest: How are they garbage?
Justin: Because none of them land.
None of them land.
Do you know what the year of Jubilee is?
Guest: Yes, but no.
Justin: Okay, what happens in the year of Jubilee?
Guest: I disfruited, no.
Justin: What happens during the Jubilee?
Guest: Did I not disprove your point?
Justin: You didn't.
You're cooking yourself.
What happens during the Jubilee?
Guest: Because you said God said okay to all his slaves.
Justin: What happens during the Jubilee?
Guest: Don't get out of topic.
Justin: I'm responding to the verse you brought up, Nitwit.
During the year of Jubilee, what happens?
Guest: And I'm not talking about that.
Justin: I'm talking about your-
You are.
Guest: You brought it up.
Statement.
Justin: All right, I'll break it down since you're not smart enough to gather it.
It says every seventh year, you shall grant remission of debts.
And these are debts to the Hebrews, not to the foreigners.
And this is the manner of remission.
Every creditor shall remit the claim that is held against a neighbor,
not exacting it because the Lord's remission has been proclaimed.
Of a foreigner, you may exact it.
You do not remit the debt of a foreigner.
You keep cooking yourself over and over again.
You must be a sadomasochist.
Guest: Your original claim was that it was okay for God to own slaves.
God said you can do it.
He said it to the Israelites after they were enslaved for 430 years.
Justin: God said you can do it.
I know.
We keep going back to this.
Guest: Okay, so I did refute your claim.
Justin: When God says you can do it, it means you can do it.
Guest: Well, he said under one condition.
If you were enslaved and you were an Israelite, which is the context,
you can own a slave up to six years and free them to seven.
Justin: Wrong.
We'll read it again.
We'll try this again.
The condition is that if they're a foreigner, they can be your property for life.
It says you may also acquire them from among the aliens residing with you
and from their families who have been, I'm sorry,
family who are with you have been born in your land.
They may be your property.
You may keep them as a possession for your children after you,
for them to inherit as property.
In the Hebrew, it actually says le'olam, which means forever,
which is why a lot of translations say that they will be your property forever
or they will say they'll be your permanent property.
And he ran.
I didn't cut him, guys.
He cooked.
Imagine coming in with that amount of gusto, having not read any of it,
literally just Googling talking points, trying to find anything that would land.
These people are embarrassing.